Tracey Emin is one of the leading lights
of British art today.
She's one of the big figures. There's no
question about that. She's one of the
most compelling figures and her work is
incredibly charismatic.
>> My sister makes her own rod for her own
back being Tracey Emin, the weird wacky
artist. She's out to shock people to
make a name for herself in London.
>> She's a big national British institution
like Morecambe and Wise or Quentin
Crisp.
But she either is kind of a genius and a
wonderful thing and an extraordinary
thing or too much of a charlatan or a
fake or a loser.
>> Being an artist, you have to have an
ego.
And for me, sexuality is part of my ego.
People say that my work's
tediously narcissistic and I But then
those people don't like me. They don't
like what I stand for. They don't like
my accent. They don't like my attitude.
And guess what? I'm not making my work
for them anyway.
I have really good ideas when I'm
feeling sexy.
I'm talking about an inner feeling. I'm
talking about how your blood moves
around your body, how your eyes might
twinkle, how your mouth might slightly
smirk, and people say things or
whatever, how your hair may feel. I
mean, Christ, so what? We came from sex,
didn't we? We came from love. So, why
not be able to use that as a vehicle of
expression?
>> She makes these wonderfully edgy,
vulnerable, childlike drawings, which
one can buy a unique drawing of Tracey
Emin for between, you know, £1,500 and
£3,000, depending on the size of it. And
yet, she then makes sculptures, she
makes films, she makes she does
performances. So, you have an extremely
eclectic output. She's just recently had
a hugely successful show in New York
with
works selling up to £35,000.
And yet, there is the central issue that
is Tracey Emin. Her work is about
herself, and her work comes from her
personal experiences.
>> The The first thing that really
impressed me was the video of her that
she ends up dancing, where she talks
about, you know, her life in Margate,
and being teased because she was
exploring her early sexuality.
>> By the time I was 15, I'd stopped
shagging.
But, I was still flesh.
And I thought with my body.
But, now it was different.
Now, it was me and dancing.
Then the big one came, the local finals.
And as I started to dance, people
started to clap. I was going to win.
And then they started.
Slag. slag slag
a gang of blokes most of whom I'd had
sex with at some time or other
were chanting slag
until in the end I couldn't hear the
music anymore
or the people clapping
my head was spinning and I was crying
I'd lost it
I ran off the dance floor out of the
club down the steps to the sea
and I thought I'm leaving this place I'm
getting out of here
I'm better than all of them I'm free and
I left Margate and I left those boys
Shane Eddie Tommy Doug Richard
this one's for you
>> [music]
>> I've always liked her work because you
know real art to me
primarily [music] about emotions and
there's very few artists that express
them as clearly and as succinctly and as
bravely as Tracey
>> and she's quite a handful and you know
she's like demanding and manipulative
and all of those things but at the same
time I think her work is liberating for
lots of people
>> I don't understand how one how you can
say that I mean it's about Tracey and
maybe other people can maybe have some
kind of
uh empathy with that but actually in the
end it's all about Tracey and it's
incredibly selfish
>> but that that that's within the small
>> that's what's interesting about it and
her friends I'm sure there's zillions of
women in Britain that feel somehow a
little bit encouraged and uh supported
through her work
>> I mean I don't know if I want her to be
a role model you know I don't know
whether I don't know if I want my sister
to grow up as one of the Tracey Emins
>> why
>> no but there's only one Tracey Emin
>> why why why what do you mean by that
that's such a weird thing to say what do
you mean by that? Why?
>> Um, because
I think that
there's a lot of things that she's not
going to have in her life that that
it'd be nice if she did. Children are
the obvious things.
>> Yeah, there again you're being very
subjective, aren't you?
>> She's she's the kind of single person's
artist, isn't she?
>> Well, I agree with you. I've got a
daughter and I wouldn't like
to think of her having to go through
some of the things Tracey's gone through
in her life.
But
then again
we all have to go through horrible
things, don't we?
>> This is all the cuttings that I've saved
of Tracey's
from a long time ago and I just kept
every one of them. Maybe 100? Maybe.
Must be, actually.
I was very proud of her because of some
of the lovely things that said about
her, some of the not so nice things said
about her.
It says
"I slept with all the good men in
Margate and I don't regret it."
And it says that there were 30 good men,
but I don't really think there were 30
good men in Margate at that time.
But no, I hated it. Tracey did as well,
but
there was nothing we could do about it
once they'd put it in the paper.
Like her tent when she all the people
she ever slept with
or people straight away. Imagine it's
all the men, but it isn't. It was just
through her life the people she'd
actually been
to bed with. Even Paul twins in the womb
she slept with and her nanny Plum she
called it she slept with. It was just
everybody she slept with.
When she was nominated for the Turner
Prize
they didn't write something like Tracey
Emin of Margate. They'd put "Our Trace
may be up" That's her their words. "Our
Trace" I've still got the paper. Could
be up for a mega prize.
>> I was really surprised I was nominated
for the Turner Prize this year because
after being really drunk after Turner
Prize discussion panel thing like is it
Peyton dead or whatever it was, I
thought I'd just completely blown it
anyway. Cuz I thought they're never
going to let a girl like me prance
around the tape before few of cameras
and live television ever again.
>> Have a look at this.
>> Question, are there really real people
in England watching this program now?
Are they really watching? Are they
really watching it?
Real people watching this program.
>> Why are you asking that question?
>> They're probably as real as you are,
Tracey. Let's face it.
>> They're just 25 minutes behind us. Think
about that.
>> We were at the dinner at the Tate
Gallery of Turner Prize and there was a
kind of group of so-called distinguished
people including myself,
uh, sitting around.
Tracey was also invited as a
distinguished person. But she was a
little bit drunk. She started taking the
piss and she became the star of the
evening and quite rightly too. I mean
the thing about artists, talk about it
less and look at it more
and I think that's what she was saying
somehow.
>> I'm an artist here from from that show.
From the Sensation, I'm here. I'm drunk.
Had a good night out with my friends.
I'm leaving now. I'll be with my
friends. I'll be leaving my mom. I'll
phone her.
And she's going to be embarrassed about
this conversation. It's live. But I
don't care. I think you're a [__] about
it.
>> I was sitting quite comfortably watching
the television.
And then suddenly I just turned it off.
Cuz I thought that's that's not Tracey.
It can't be.
And then I
then I think that I think that next day
she phoned me.
And I said, you know, don't worry. I'm
saying, Tracey, that was awful. She
says, don't worry about it, Mom.
And then someone of somebody else rang
me and said, don't worry about it. It's
You know, she didn't really do anything
wrong. She was just saying what she
thought."
>> You people aren't relating to me now.
You've lost me. You've lost me
completely.
>> So, you don't You don't think it is a
generational thing?
>> There's no way with this [__] mic on
me. On No, I want to put it off. I want
to be free.
Do you understand?
>> Well,
it's a great painting by the great
painting by Tracey Emin, Autumnal
Storms.
Thanks.
>> My work is self-portraiture, definitely.
So, if I do a drawing of a say
13-year-old girl, it's actually a
drawing of myself from my own memory of
myself, but it doesn't necessarily look
like me.
Um, but it's just the figure that I
identify with.
But, it's almost like a fingerprint of
myself or something.
When I started drawing again after years
of not drawing, I started by doing a
series called Illustrations from Memory.
So, I I thought of something which
happened to me, and then I illustrated
it on paper. And that way, I could
justify myself in doing a drawing after
so many years of not doing any.
>> [snorts]
>> Well, I'd always really wanted to buy a
piece of Tracey's. And to me, Tracey's
always been a poet and a storyteller as
much as she's been an artist and a
painter and a drawer.
So, I always wanted a piece which really
told me something about Tracey's life
and about Tracey herself. And From a
Week in Hell was the first piece of
Tracey's that I ever bought. Here, we
have a um
uh it's a prose poem depiction of her
week. Friday.
Woke up having sex with a terrible
hangover.
Ran to the bathroom to throw up,
[__] at the same time. Holding onto
the pan, small white balls of foam
cascading out of my mouth.
My whole body shaking.
My eyes ready to burst, swearing to God
I'd never drink again.
Threw up nine more times that day.
Saturday and Sunday.
Spent the whole weekend in bed,
depressed, trying to recover while scabs
break out all over my chin.
Monday. Woke up with horrendous
toothache. Took some painkillers and
dabbed on some oil of cloves. Went to
pick up my pills too late, and too late
by two [__] hours for the
morning-after pill.
Had to be fitted with an IUD.
A piece of copper wire wrapped around a
plastic hook.
Tuesday. Went to St. Thomas's Hospital
for lung scan test and chest medical.
Was told I had emphysema.
A week in hell um
echoes of many experiences I've gone
through in my life myself. But I But I
think it's for all of us. It's um
Tra- Tracy gets really down and into the
depths of the soul.
>> And I suppose the blankets are the
closest things really that I get to like
paintings. Cuz you're dealing with
textures and colors and tones, layering.
But I think what's brilliant is that
that they actually do from a distance
look quite pretty.
And then when people get close up, they
have to read
the unbearable truth.
When I was young, I had sex with someone
uh when I was about 13, 14. 13,
actually.
And I had sex with someone on their way
home and their mate was with them, so
their mate had to like sit behind a
hedge or something. It was on a green in
Margate.
When I stood up to pull my knickers up,
one of them pointed and sort of said,
"Yeah, look at that ugly cunt." They
were actually talking about what was
between my legs.
And I just looked at them and I thought,
"No, you've got it all wrong. You're the
ugly cunts."
>> Tracey is not secure. She's totally
insecure and and but but by acting a
certain way you can you can feel much
better and I think she she knows that
anyways.
It's the sort of ego side. Of course,
everybody's got an ego, but I think it
comes out much more with Tracey because
she has got a lot more kind of
insecurities about about things in
general.
>> The first blanket I sold, I was actually
really crying.
And it was in New York and it had been
on my bed for 2 days and and the day
that it sold, I went to bed sort of like
half cuddling it. Thinking, "Oh, what
have I done? I shouldn't have sold my
blanket. I shouldn't have done it." And
that blanket had that blanket a third of
it was made from the blanket which I had
on my bed when I was little girl.
And it also had a large piece of fabric
on it from our sofa when I was 4 years
old. And I think when you spend so long
sewing all the blankets, they end up
smelling, which is quite weird. Don't
ask me what of. No, of like like things
being knocked off, cigarettes or just or
just of the life.
And the tent had an exceptionally strong
smell.
Eating in it, you know, falling asleep
in it, sweating in it.
And of course, it uses the euphemism of
sleep.
And there are some people I've actually
had sex with.
>> A lot of the things seem too loose, too
formless for me to see them lasting in
the sense of meaning [music] anything to
future generations.
The big exception I make I could point
to other things too, but it's the tent.
It was as full of her life as it was of
air. It's almost as though her life had
inflated the tent to give it that the
rounded shape.
Now, I've been talking about it as
though it was some sort of great symbol.
And that indeed is what it is.
Tracey is a nomad, I think. I don't
think she's a naturally rooted person.
So, the tent fits that very well.
>> Well, that's Turkish Cypriot. When I was
a little girl, we used I used to speak
Turkish up until I was four or whatever,
and I just lost it when I went to
school, same as my twin brother, Paul.
My dad took me to to Cyprus and Turkey
when I was um 20, when I was in a quite
a bad mentally quite bad way.
The idea was, "I'm taking you home."
Suddenly, I realized that I had all this
culture and all this side of me.
And suddenly, to be back in this kind of
um Mediterranean environment, I realized
just how un-British I was, and it was
really good for me. But then, as it went
on, I've become more and more extreme.
You can still see me with a dagger
between my teeth and the long red
fingernails, you know. I don't think
I'll come across very English at all.
>> She's got everything she needs. She's an
artist, and she don't look back.
She's got everything she needs. She's an
artist, she don't look back.
>> That tree.
That tree.
>> So, you can take the dark out of the
nighttime and
paint the daytime black.
She wears an Egyptian red ring. It
sparkles before she speaks.
>> Beautiful one.
>> [music]
>> Quickly, cuz the film's going to run
out.
>> She's a hypnotist collector. Here
are the walking dead, P.
>> Into the distance.
You're coming back. [screaming]
>> All right, I'll go find
>> Don't come back, Daddy. Just keep
walking.
>> Okay.
>> Keep walking.
I think you've ruined it.
It's going to run out any second now.
Go.
Keep going.
>> That's it.
>> Oh, no.
>> Oh, sorry. I
couldn't help me. I couldn't help you.
>> back and do it again.
>> I couldn't help me.
Brilliant. Excellent. It wasn't
difficult, was it? I'm happy with that.
>> He
>> Yeah.
>> Lie down on his own Sunday. Salute him
when his birthday come.
Lie down on his own Sunday. [music]
Salute him when his birthday come.
>> Come on. No, no.
I'm just
No, I'm not
>> For Halloween, give her a trumpet and
for Christmas, buy her a drum.
>> I've been raised on gifts, but my dad
has promised [music] me and promises
that he's never been able to fulfill
again and again and again.
>> Tracy, I'll tell you something.
>> I'm not going to move to surprise you as
well.
>> No.
If you want this olive tree in this
land, it's yours.
>> it's a surprise, I don't want to know
about that. I don't want to know about
the [__] program.
>> All right, take it all. Take it all.
>> No.
>> Can you
>> I'm not interested in the remotest. It's
impossible.
I'm not having stuff like that. Not
impossible, Daddy. Sorry.
>> Okay, my darling.
All right.
>> She's not materialistic, so.
>> I'm used to promises from my dad that
aren't kept, but now that I'm older,
I kind of understand that it's part of
He's given me so much more,
you know, that I I don't I don't have a
grudge with him against it. I just don't
fall for it anymore like I used to, but
I still behave in the same bratty way
when he attempts to do it. But, you
never know, maybe one day he'll come up
trumps. But, the important thing with me
is I've done everything myself.
So, I don't suddenly don't want my dad
to kind of like, you know,
give me some
golden plate or whatever, cuz it it's
never been like that, ever.
Do you ever regret not spending more
time with me and Paul when we were
little?
>> Yes.
>> When you weren't around, I was um
very vulnerable.
There were times when things happened to
me, which I always felt that were really
terribly wrong.
>> Well, I didn't knew that. Your mother
never said anything.
>> Well, she didn't She didn't know. And
even if she did know, she would be in
denial. She would be unaware. She would
be in denial. She would be unaware.
>> take anything away from you.
>> Looking back on your life, do you think
it was wrong or right to have
like a mistress and a wife for so long?
>> No.
>> Enjoyed every minute of it.
>> Okay, then. How many children have you
got?
>> Official?
>> Official.
>> Five.
How many unofficial?
>> About 18.
Yes, about 18 of them.
>> 18?
>> Yeah.
>> Now, the last time it was 11, about 10
years ago we spoke.
>> No, no, no, no, no.
>> 18?
>> 18. Five to you, one three the others,
five. Yes.
23.
>> 23 children?
>> That I know
>> That you know of?
>> No, I don't know if that's true, but
everybody was happy.
>> [laughter]
>> Everybody was happy.
>> And did you You didn't plan to have me
and Paul, did you?
>> No, we wanted it desperately.
But, we didn't knew that it would be
twins.
>> But, don't you think you were quite
irresponsible for quite a lot of years
when you went off?
>> I was drunk.
And it
It was I was
The truth, I mean, most of the time I
was
>> you weren't drunk when we were born. You
become tea total.
>> No, no, yes. I yes.
Because I I gave up drinking when when
your mother told me that you were she
was pregnant.
And maybe it maybe part of that changed
my life.
>> Big big question. Do you think drinking,
cuz Paul and I both drink quite heavily,
which you and Mom seem cool about, you
don't seem to you know, you've never
given us any hassle or any trouble about
it. But, do you think that drinking
could be hereditary maybe?
>> No.
No.
I don't believe that.
It's you which you turn yourself into a
habitual drinker.
>> Do you get more fun when I'm drunk or
when I'm sober?
I'm more fun when I'm drunk.
>> Yes, you are. More joyful.
>> Yeah. And do you think I'm just moody
and irritable when I'm sober?
>> Well, first thing in the morning, like
today this morning, always you're like
that.
>> Yeah.
>> Teresa, I will never tell you what to do
with your life or drinking or habit or
whatever you want to do unless you
realize yourself.
You had all that freedom from childhood.
>> Like the sea, we keep turning. Like
time, life keeps moving.
Joined together by eternity.
By blood,
the stars, the sun, and the moon.
I love you, Daddy.
>> Emmen used to take me aside and give me
advice about how to treat his princess
occasionally. And I told Tracy that if
he didn't stop if she didn't stop in
talking to me, I would have nothing to
do with her.
And she did stop in talking to me. He
give I think Emmen gives misinformation.
Personally.
I think there's a lot of
a lot of Tracy's blindness comes from
Emmen's blindness.
When I first met her, she was studying
fashion and her work was she did she had
a little sketchbook. She did interiors
of her bedroom and maybe her nan
pictures at home. And she had a very low
opinion of them, but I encouraged her
that I thought it was good to do
anything.
So it all fell apart she did when she
went up to Germany with her dad on a
business trip.
It's her instructions that make your
very own MTB because I wanted to live on
a motor torpedo boat. So this is how you
make one.
She stopped doing fashion. And she went
to Maidstone to do print making. I've
got one of the things of the first
sexual thing she did which were pictures
of me and her.
>> When she was at Maidstone, she worked in
the print making department and had a
little corner of her own.
And I think tutors there were a bit um
shame-faced about this particular corner
of because it was full of images that
some people would rather not see. I mean
you can see the very sexually explicit
images and she was always tremendously
uh
daring in her use of subject matter. Um
very very bold and following the German
expressionist tradition.
But using her own personal experience
as
for her imagery.
>> Everything I did between the age of say
19 and 20 to 23 was like a gut reaction.
It was like just one massive [__] or one
massive vomit. There wasn't actually
much thought behind it. It was more like
an impulse like a kind of reaction. I
would look at books on Edvard Munch or
Käthe Kollwitz or even Sheila and then
just run off and do my own versions.
And then when I then I did an MA at the
Royal College of Art for 2 years doing
painting which was only painting and I
was very unhappy student there. It was
not particularly good conducive place
for me.
>> I went to see her after she left the
Royal College
when she had a studio in South London
and um
she was
very ill and
quite poverty-stricken and saw this um
among pieces she had there and it was
quite different from anything I'd seen
of hers before. I asked her if she
wanted to sell it and what she wanted
for it
and she wanted she said um she'd like 10
pounds.
I
knew that by any standards it was worth
more than that so I I gave her 100
pounds.
>> [music]
>> I was quite a late developer in
commercially being accepted as an artist
or getting some respect.
About 2 years ago it worked out that I
was going to probably a different
country almost every week for art and
for exhibitions and staying in really
fantastic hotels like this one, you
know, and always five star except I was
becoming unbearably lonely. I would just
watch MTV, raid the mini bar, drink at
the whole contents, write as many
letters as I could on scraps of paper.
So ultimately in the end my mini bar
bill or my fax and telephone bill, would
often be much more than the actual hotel
room. So, I got kind of sick and like,
you know, I always said, you know, what
you do is just stay in your room and
masturbate or something, you know. That
is most people's options. Or,
alternatively, get out on the streets
and start looking for it.
I'd not had sex for about a year or
something.
And uh
it's all I thought about, really.
So, it was kind of becoming a bit
dangerous.
So, I decided to make a film about this
kind of frustration. And then, last
year, me and Boy George actually turned
words into a very nice disco song.
>> [music]
[music]
>> And every part of my body is bleeding, a
wound of desire. And I know [music] it's
safer to be alone. The kiss you left
behind, the sweet smell of desire.
After art college, I did actually
destroy nearly all my work in 1991.
And this came about, I think, through my
abortions. I decided I didn't want to be
like that anymore. There was enough [__]
in the world, and I really didn't need
to put any more [__]
The fact that I was a failure as a
painter, a failure as an artist, and
then having an abortion gave me another
level of failure as a human being.
>> [music]
>> Middle of 1992, committed emotional
suicide. Emotional suicide is killing
yourself without dying. [music]
Destroying each friendship and
relationship one by one till I was
alone. Destroyed all my art, left my
studio, threw away my curtains, my
carpet, my cushions, my comfort. Made my
home into a cell and waited.
>> [music]
>> I felt like I'd lost everything and
everything was very difficult. And I was
down in Margate.
And I wrote on the sea wall, I need art
like I need God. And stood back,
couldn't believe what I'd written. I
hadn't even thought about it. It just
was a like a subconscious thing.
>> [music]
>> And I thought about death and I thought
about despair and all those kind of
moments where and and like when you lose
lovers and you lose you feel like life
you're losing grip of life.
>> [music]
[singing]
>> And something good happens and you find
your way again. And and I thought about
art, how many times I've left it and
decided I don't want anything more to do
with it and it always finds me.
1992, asked people to invest in my
creative potential.
Met Sarah Lucas.
January 1993, started the shop with
Sarah.
>> [music]
[music]
>> I think the shop was a good place to
actually do all these bits and pieces
pieces because Tracey did do a lot of
ephemeral um small bits of work and to
actually have a place that could
actually be able to you could actually
see those the context of the shop was
quite good and I think the idea of the
shop was great anyway and so I think
actually I think that did help Tracey's
art as well an awful lot.
>> Okay.
You're very what?
Pissed and correct.
>> Good [laughter] morning, this is Perry.
>> Your daughter's very hairy ROUND THE
HOLE.
>> [laughter]
>> I WENT TO LOOK AROUND AND
I THOUGHT, "GOD, this is hilarious. It's
just all crap." And I came back
downstairs. Tracy said, "What do you
think?" She said, "It's all crap."
And she just sort of burst out laughing
as though like I just got the point of
the whole thing and I actually thought,
"Yeah, I I like this place."
After the shop closed, it only was open
for 6 months.
Sarah went back to making art again and
she had a kind of, you know, way of
doing things. She had collectors. She
had a gallery to work with. But Tracy
had nothing.
>> I first met Tracy in a pub and this very
beguiling wide-eyed girl
came over. She asked, "If If you give me
10 quid,
I'll send you four letters over the next
year."
Sure enough, about
two or three months later when I'd
completely forgotten the evening,
a letter came through my uh
post box. And there was an account of a
very difficult period in her life when
she had her first abortion. And around
that time I invited Tracy to make an
exhibition here in White Cube. So I
said, "Why don't you try and make a kind
of homage to your life? You must have
the space. You can do whatever you like.
But what I what really excites me about
your work is the fact that you're
sharing what is extraordinarily personal
details."
She devoted a section of the exhibition
to photographs of every painting that
she'd made from her days uh
at art school. But she destroyed these
paintings, but she photographed each and
every one of them. And as a kind of
homage to this earlier struggling
period, she then went on to title the
show "My Major Retrospective." I think
believing that this might be the only
opportunity she'd ever get to have an
exhibition.
>> Charles, the color
that we painted this wall has been
chosen by Tracy.
Um
according to her instructions based on
the on the color on this catalog cover.
But I
>> What what's the significance of that?
>> It's her sort of trademark blue.
>> So, where is the work?
>> The work, I believe, at this very
moment, um nearly half past 5:00 on
Monday, the day before the show, is in
Tracy's head. She's ill, and um
I don't think she's had the opportunity
to do the work. So,
we know I know her to be conscientious
and reliable. Therefore, I expect her to
be up all night.
>> I'm sure, but there's still 24 hours. It
is is a pretty short space of time.
>> Yes.
>> Originally, we were just going to have a
sort of small drawing and text piece. I
mean, it certainly wouldn't have covered
that wall. I mean, how are we going to
fill that? Well, how is she going to
fill it? Do we know?
>> No, we're not sure of the details. I
imagine
that Tracy's going to come with some
drawings and text, and that these will
be placed strategically over the wall.
>> Well, we need to do now is see it.
>> Yeah.
>> My exhibition at White Cube has become a
major retrospective. There was a wall of
memorabilia, and I showed like a uh uh
I called them families. Each piece had
was like a family. And one of them, I
think, was was was the most um precious
and most seminal was my uncle Colin,
which was mementos about my uncle Colin.
And there there was a text with it,
which explained his death, how he died
in a car crash by becoming decapitated.
Uh a certain ton juggernaut lorry pushed
his car underneath a bus
at Chingford traffic lights.
And the thing which caught most people's
I think imagination was a packet of
Benson Hedges cigarettes that he was
actually holding at the time of his
death.
>> I did think it was really wonderful.
I just because it I felt that he was
there. I felt that Colleen was there
when she made this work.
Cuz at the time when Colleen got killed,
it did disrupt the whole of the family.
And when she made this work, it just we
just felt that he was still here.
Strange actually, isn't it? But how we
felt about it.
>> All artists have a backbone to what they
do. So, some people it could be
photography, some people film, some
people sculpture. And for me, the the
essence and the backbone of what I do is
the written word, definitely.
>> He slipped his arm around my shoulder
and said, "How about a New Year's Eve
kiss then?"
We stood in the doorway at Burton's and
started snogging. He put his hand down
my top and at the same time pushing me
against the wall, he pulled my skirt up.
And I began to worry.
This isn't what I wanted. He was older
than me.
And everybody knew he'd broken into
girls before and I didn't want to be.
"No," I said, "Get off, please. No,
you're hurting me."
>> When I had the book was finished, I
said, "Why don't we just drive across
America and do a big huge reading tour?"
And one day Tracy said, "You know, I'm
going to take my nan's chair with me."
Which she's sat in her flat for as long
as I can ever remember, this funny old
green chair.
And she said, "And I think what I'll do
as well is I think I'll decorate it and
sort of tell a few stories on it, make
it into a piece of art."
Her nan had said to her something many
years ago. Um there's a lot of money in
chairs.
Meaning really that when you look behind
chairs, you know, when you need to buy
us a few, you know, some [__] or a
bottle of beer or something, you can get
some money out. This chair was probably
worth £4.
And now it's probably priceless.
That's art for you.
It's a lot of money in chairs.
>> Tracey's work works as a kind of collage
of different objects. When you see it in
the show, it's I don't think seeing one
piece in isolation works so much for me
as to see a whole group of
bits of Tracey's work. To have lots of
other bits feeding off each other.
>> Lies and Britain, you know, like you
made that something joining.
I don't think that people really saw
Tracey's work as a sort of cohesive
thing until her solo show at the South
London Gallery.
You could actually see that there was
something here which kind of connected
up and there was quite a big
story going on.
Tracey and her twin Paul gone their own
separate ways, I think, but up until a
certain point they were very, very
close.
>> I'm proud of her. Yeah, don't get me
wrong. Like anybody that's doing well,
anybody that can sell an old bit of rope
like and demand thousands of pounds
worth for it. Fair play to her. Fair
play to her. But is that art?
Or is that somebody pulling the wool
over somebody's [music] eyes? That is my
comment on modern art. It's a total load
of bollocks.
>> [music]
[singing]
>> A sensitive letter about Paul's past
was incorporated into one of her pieces
of work.
And later on it appeared in a television
program about collectors. So, Paul's
private life became public property.
>> She's just literally out to shock.
And suddenly,
the wrong person watched that program,
and I lost my contract.
I actually sit here. I've started my own
life for 7 years.
Been as good as gold, going to work
every day, getting these contracts.
Takes one bit of snippet on TV, put one
letter in a collage, and suddenly I'm
ruined. That's not fair, mate.
The only way that I can actually see
getting a positive result out of this
was actually making this statement on
television today to say, "Please leave
Paul Em alone, cuz he doesn't want
nothing to do with Tracey Emin's artwork
anymore."
>> Previously, my family have actually
helped me make a lot of my work with the
memorabilia and all the objects and
talking about them and stories. But, I
think a lot of time I'm making them
cringe. It's okay for me living in
London in this sort of metropolitan
lifestyle, but it's not very good in
Margate if people know your private
business from your past.
I regret things. And
sadly enough now,
I'm you know, I'm going to either change
my my work is going to have to change or
I'm going to be censored.
Unfortunately, by my family. So, if
that's the way it is, that's the way it
is. I have to respect people that I
love.
>> I was just thinking about when we used
to jump off that thing.
>> Yeah, it looks like a 100
ft high now, isn't it?
>> Yeah, would you do it now?
>> I might do it if it was a sunny day, but
>> No, you wouldn't. No way. No way.
>> No, it's going to be a bit too cold for
that. There ain't no steps here anymore,
either.
>> No, everything's gone rusty and old.
>> Yeah.
>> And the skyline looks really stupid
without the big wheel.
>> Yeah. Why do you think we got a
spotlight coming out in the winter when
all the storms were going?
Used to get as close as you
would you could and wait for a big wave
and hang on to something.
You're lucky you're not dead.
>> Lucky we're not dead anyway.
This really is desolate.
>> No sun deck. Used to go swimming. We
used to go swimming out there as well.
>> I'd have a cigarette but I don't
smoke.
>> Yeah, I can still swim really
brilliantly. I swim nearly every day
now. Not every day but four times a
week. I swim in the swimming pool. I
swim
about
like a kilometer at a time.
>> Do you want to try and dive one of these
or not?
>> No, I've got no polite.
To be a a good artist or to or to be
respected, it doesn't mean to say that
you have to be a worthy, lock yourself
in your garrison, wear dungarees,
you know, wear your workman's boots,
have your brushes in your pocket and
kind of look forward to your one-man
solo show every 2 years. It isn't like
that being an artist anymore cuz I think
the role of the artist as we go into the
next millennium is definitely to be a
communicator of different mediums and
different ideas.
>> So this is Jazz FM 194.9 and Gideon Co
with you till 6:00. As of today, the
Blue Gallery on Walton Street is hosting
Temple of Diana which comprises various
artworks on the subject of the late
Diana, Princess of Wales and it includes
the artwork of Tracey Emin who joins me
now. How are you doing?
>> All right.
>> Now then, the subject you were given was
Diana, Princess of Wales. What have you
actually come up with?
>> I've actually come up with a handful of
what could be considered quite scrappy,
fresh, kind of naive-looking drawings.
My usual kind of thing.
But I wish I'd have spent longer doing
the drawings, maybe made a lot more.
>> So, what does Diana bring to mind for
you, then?
>> Well, I really hate the royal family and
think that they should have been like
either shot a long time ago or at least
been made to give up all their money
until Diana. And I kind of quite like
the way that she almost brought them
down single-handedly.
And I see her as quite a good modern
icon. It's pretty difficult for me to do
drawings about someone else and not me.
I must But I did have lots of ideas.
>> Uh they're very moving. Thank you very
much, Tracey.
>> They're quite sentimental, I think.
There's absolutely nothing cynical about
it whatsoever.
>> About 5 years down the line, what would
you like to be doing?
>> I'd like to be living in a really big
sort of house by the sea with a nice
swimming pool in the back garden,
sunbathing.
>> And making what, though?
>> Doing the same as what I'm doing now,
but in a nice environment.
>> Tracey's got this idea that you don't
need to be a starving artist in a garret
to make art. But the tent, neon signs,
her book,
and the blankets, the drawings,
everything, it all came from being in a
position of having no money to buy cheap
brandy.
>> The calendar's for a car company,
Daewoo. And they've asked certain
artists and people to do a month. My
month is October, which is breast cancer
awareness month. Yeah, it was my idea,
yeah.
Yeah. Just to have my tits in it,
really.
So, it's car effort, isn't it? It's car
calendar. Where's it going to be hung?
Garages, you know. What What are these
men in garages want to see, these
mechanics?
I don't want to look a hunchback,
exactly.
And I don't want to look hangdog. I want
to
have some kind of dignity about this
whole situation.
>> She has called herself Mad Tracey from
Margate.
But now I think that Tracey would prefer
to see herself as sensible, sane
Tracey from Shoreditch.
>> What the hell's selling out?
The idea of making the same thing again
and again and again, it would kill me. I
really do I need to get some more felt.
I'm just going to pop downstairs and get
that. You don't have to follow me. You
can Even with each blanket with each
blanket would be very different.
I've got this white felt cuz I'm going
to make a blanket. This is a story about
me wetting the bed in Austria. I'm
actually going to sew the white
uh felt onto a stained pissy sheet.
So, I'm really looking forward to that
one, but obviously I need a lot of white
felt cuz all the text is just going to
be white and it's just going to tell the
story of me wetting the bed. And then
every day tearing up the sheet into tiny
pieces and burying it in the snow.
Hence, that's why I want everything to
be white and yellow. So, I'm going to
just get have to get a sheet and then
just piss all over it.
So, but unartistically, I just want to
be natural. I probably should lay down
cuz if you stand up, it will go like a
it will actually make a pattern, won't
it?
>> Let's get this right. You like her
because you think she's a new type of
artist for the '90s. Is that right?
>> I think she's a person who's
successfully made herself into a
larger-than-life character. At the
moment, there's such an elastic idea
about what art is that she can make
herself seem like a thing called a
conceptual artist. No one knows what
that is, but she seems to have made
herself into one.
>> Do you trust her? Do you believe that
it's coming from the heart rather than
than from some kind of position of
knowledge that people reading or
watching this will be moved by it or
titillated by it?
>> Yeah, that's a good question.
Cuz I'm not sure what it is. I believe
something about what she's doing. I'm
not sure if I believe that her pain is
any more important than anyone else's.
>> That's what I meant, yeah.
>> Yeah, no, I think she is the same as
anyone else. She's a kind of over every
woman in that sense.
>> But that's what makes her a good artist,
isn't it?
>> Yeah, she can access something that
people want to know. People can identify
with her.
>> She's used real things. She puts them
together, but she turns them into
something.
>> Yeah, that's why it's art and it's not a
bore in the pub,
>> You know. Yes.
>> crying into their beer and telling you
about their problems.
>> That's right. Unlike us two.
>> Yeah, us old farts, yeah.
>> Everyone has their cross to bear, and it
doesn't matter how much pain I've been
in my life, when I actually really
balance it up,
um I haven't really suffered that much.
But saying that, I think I would still
give up all the art today at this
instant not to have the the sort of
volatile emotional feelings that I've
had or had to go through.
And it's the fact that I've used them to
make work. I've turned it around. I've
turned the bad things around to make
something good.
Rather than just saying, oh, life's
terrible, you know, I'm destroyed. I've
just turned it all around.
>> She's born to win the Turner Prize.
She's born to be a dame. You know, when
she is 55, she will be a dame. She's
born to be on stage, and I'm sure she's
in pain whenever she's not on the stage.
When she's on stage, she's acting the
pain. And
so, if she got the prize, she would
[music]
make a fabulously drunken speech of
thanks and forget everyone's name, get
the names mixed up and so forth.
>> Sorry, gentlemen, I'm afraid you've been
asked to leave this establishment. Can I
follow you with your drinks? I'm just
the barmaid, okay? I just work here.
>> Well, I'm sure we deserve to be checked
out.
>> There's nothing worse than warm men with
warm beer.
>> Tracey, they've got one bottle each. You
can shout them.
>> Right up
the bottom.
>> [laughter]
>> She'll come.
She'll come.
>> [music]
>> She'll lay believe
on you.
Skin sweet with musky oil,
the lady from another greening show.
Cologne
she wears.
Selva
and America. [singing]
She'll drive a big old car.
>> [music]
>> A beat-up
old Canasta.
>> [music]